How do you get a new product off the
ground? And when you're just starting
out, where do those first real users
actually come from? You see, most people
aren't early adopters. Ask yourself, how
many products do you use today that you
were among the first 10 users of? For
most people, the answer is zero. Almost
no one wants to be a startup's first
paying customer, yet every great product
still manages to find a few people
willing to take that leap. The earliest
version of your product only needs to do
one thing: survive contact with a tiny
group of people who might actually try
it. You're not building the final form.
You're building something that can
evolve. When you're starting out, you
don't just need a minimum viable
product. You need a minimum evolvable
product. And I'm going to show you how
to find one.
Before you get discouraged, there are
people who love being early adopters.
One of my colleagues, Gustav, worked at
Airbnb for years and enjoyed trying out
products from startups and bringing them
into the company. Others have such a
burning issue that they're willing to
give any new product a shot if it looks
like it could make their life easier.
For example, when my team needed to ship
our first inference API, we wanted to
ship it fast and didn't want to deal
with figuring out billing or public
endpoint. Within 3 days, I found and
paid a startup whose product solved that
issue for us. I was their first
customer. Their size or reputation
didn't matter. Our problem did. So, we
took a chance on them and they
delivered. The lesson is simple. Finding
your first users is more of a search
problem than a persuasion problem.
You're looking for the Gustavs and Ankas
of the world. The ones who try new
things or have a burning need that you
can solve. This has a few
counterintuitive implications that
you're going to want to pay attention
to. Charge real money early. Early
adopters and people with a burning
problem are rarely price sensitive. The
goal here isn't revenue, it's feedback.
And paying customers give sharper
feedback than free users ever will.
You're more likely to get feedback from
an angry customer paying a lot of money
than a nobody who isn't willing to pay.
Use targeted personal outreach. The ways
you find these people probably don't
look like how you find normal people. A
billboard is way less likely to reach
them versus something like a targeted
cold email or a knock on their door.
Launch early. This is something YC has
preached from the beginning. In the
early days, you don't know much about
who these early users are, and [music]
you want to engineer a wide surface area
for them to find you. Study your early
users closely. You should be like an
anthropologist that's [music] discovered
a hidden civilization. How do they make
decisions? Why would they make the
strange choice to trust you? You want to
understand how they think and what they
want. Experiment fast and don't fear
churn. You should be running constant
experiments, pricing, landing pages,
onboarding, features, everything. At the
same time, talk to your early users and
try to make them love the product. But
don't stress if you lose one of them. If
you annoy someone, you can usually fix
it because the relationship is personal.
And if they churn, that's fine, too.
There are plenty of others who haven't
even heard of you yet. This is one of
the advantages startups have over big
companies. When you run a bad
experiment, no one writes about it.
You're fighting relevance, not
headlines. All of this may shape who
you're even building for in the
beginning. Most people don't pay for a
bunch of consumer apps. The average
personal software spend is pretty
[music] tiny. For example, mine's about
$150 a month total. Meanwhile, my
corporate card has multiple tools that
each cost more than that alone. In the
AI era, that gap matters. Consumer apps
can struggle because ads often don't
cover AI costs, and subscriptions have
to squeeze into an already small
personal budget. Of course, many
consumer companies will still be made,
but this is why many AI founders choose
to start by selling to prosumers or
businesses, or targeting users like
doctors that have high advertising
value. This leads us to an even bigger
point. Your early users don't just give
you feedback. They end up steering how
your product evolves over time. Here's
an analogy I used to help founders think
about their first users. Think of a
startup as a phylogenetic tree. Okay,
bear with me. The root node is an
amoeba, and the leaf nodes are complex
multicellular organisms like humans or
dogs. Almost every product you buy on
the market has run this evolutionary
process and morphed from an amoeba to
the maturity of a human or a dog.
Millions of users, a refined sales
pitch, and clear value. Early startups
are more like amoebas. They have just
the very basic functions needed to get
exposed to external pressures. But from
there, the founders run an evolutionary
search through the tree of potential
future directions.
Consider Tesla as a case study.
Specifically, their amoeba, the Tesla
Roadster. The lore about the Roadster is
that Tesla needed a high-margin product
to fund their capex investment to make
the Model S and eventually the Model 3
and Y. That's probably true, but there's
a second interpretation. Tesla was
searching for early adopters. They
wanted to find the people crazy enough
to buy an impractical $150,000 car that
didn't go very far, didn't fit much in
it, couldn't publicly charge anywhere,
and looked strange. Tesla's story
reveals another reality. That product
evolution is path-dependent on what the
early adopters wanted. Why does the
Tesla Model Y, a mass-market vehicle,
have a faster zero to 60 than a
Lamborghini and better tech than a BMW,
but worse suspension and comfort than a
Toyota? It turns out that early adopters
cared much more about tech and
acceleration than comfort. Would a
mass-market vehicle designed in a vacuum
have a zero to 60 of under 3 seconds?
Probably not. But it's an outcome of the
search algorithm that Tesla ran. If
early adopters were willing to pay
$150,000 for a slow, plush vehicle, I
bet Tesla's cars would look very
different today. This is the algorithm
we help founders run at YC, and it's why
your first version shouldn't just be a
minimum viable product. It should be a
minimum evolvable product. Something
simple that can respond to market
pressures and evolve into a much more
mature product. Something that will
survive contact with early users and
adapt fast based on what they push it
toward. It's freeing to know that the
product will change a lot, so it doesn't
have to be perfect from the start.
Ultimately, what it becomes will depend
on where you begin and who you begin it
with.